Guide to the Stanford University, President's Office, Commission on Undergraduate Education, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, President's Office, Commission on Undergraduate Education, records
1980-1994
1993-1994
SC1150
Stanford University. Office of the President
4 linear feet (4 boxes)
The Commission on Undergraduate Education at Stanford University was established to address fundamental issues pertaining to the undergraduate curriculum and related programs and services at Stanford. The Commision's report was released in October 1994.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Restricted until 2021. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
The Commission on Undergraduate Education (abbreviated internally as CUE) was established to address fundamental issues pertaining to the undergraduate curriculum and related programs and services at Stanford. Over a nine month period in 1993 and 1994, the commission sought input about the university’s degree requirements, major programs, advising system, residential education, academic calendar and use of technology in teaching and learning.
The Commission was comprised of fourteen faculty members, two students, two alumni, and the Vice-Provost for Institutional Planning, and was chaired by History Professor James Sheehan. Lowell Price, Senior Associate Provost for University Governance, and Administrative Assistant Mary Jane Reese performed staff duties.
The Commission’s goal was to clarify the goals of a Stanford undergraduate education and to recommend ways to insure that these programs were appropriate and effective in support of those goals. They were encouraged to pursue the broadest possible range of issues touching undergraduate education, including the curriculum, teaching practices, advising and other extra-curricular aspects of the college experience at Stanford. Within this comprehensive scope, however, the Commission was specifically charged with the following responsibilities:
-to articulate the educational goals of Stanford’s educational program to consider whether the curriculum, including the range of undergraduate degrees, majors, and distribution requirements adequately and effectively meets the needs of students
-to consider whether it is possible and desirable to give more students the opportunity to graduate in less than four years
-to consider the special educational requirements of students in the engineering and science disciplines
-to consider whether various modalities of teaching are used effectively, including individual tutorials, seminars and research projects, and to consider ways of instruction made possible by computers, video equipment and other forms of new technology
-to review the purposes and quality of ancillary services such as the undergraduate advising system and the residential education program
The Commission was asked to report its findings and make recommendations by October 1, 1994. In its final report, the commission recommended developing a new science course for non-science majors, strengthening Stanford’s writing and language requirements, redefining the Cultures, Ideas and Values courses, strengthening the advisor system, and enhancing the role of teaching in faculty selection and compensation. The commission also suggested creating a post of vice provost for undergraduate education. Their report represented the most extensive review of undergraduate education since the 1968 Study of Education at Stanford.
The preceding was adapted from the Commission’s Charge and Summary as published in its 1994 report, and a 10/12/1994 Stanford New Service press release about the report’s findings.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Office of the President; Education, Higher--Aims and objectives--California; Stanford University--Administration.; Stanford University--Curricula.; Universities and colleges--Planning.
Collection Contents
- published report and SUNS press release, 1994-10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Lowell Price's Binders with Notes Vol. 1. Meetings From 10/10/93 - 12/10/93, 1993 (Box 1)
- Lowell Price's Binders with Notes Vol. 2. Meetings From 12/3/93 - 4/19/94, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
- Lowell Price's Binders with Notes Vol. 3. Meetings From 4/25/94 - 6/4/94, 1994 (Box 1)
- Committee on Undergraduate Education Annual Reports, 1980-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- James Irvine Foundation. Expenditure Statements 10/93 - 12/94, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- James Irvine Foundation. Correspondence (Box 1)
- James Irvine Foundation. Grant Report, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- James Irvine Foundation. Commission Budget, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- James Irvine Foundation. Charge (Box 1, Folder 14)
- James Irvine Foundation. Commissioners (Box 1, Folder 15)
- James Irvine Foundation. Commission Notes (Box 1, Folder 16)
- James Irvine Foundation. James Sheehan (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Firing Line: Liberal Education [4 Part Series], 1993-06-11 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Surveys, 1990, 1992 (Box 2)
- Gerhard Casper Alumni Letter, 1993-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Mary Jane Reese To Do Items (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Jim Sheehan (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Volunteers (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Students (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Mary Jane Reese's Notes and Information (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Jim Sheehan (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Alumni Interest (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Board of Trustees Retreat, 1993-10-10 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Commission Retreat, 1993-10-16 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Bruce Johnson, SUNY (Box 2, Folder 15)
- CPPC Employer Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Fred Starr, Oberlin (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Academic Senate (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Committee on Committees (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Alumni (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Commission Research Team (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Faculty Senate, 1994-01-20 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Subcommittees (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Grant Money to Registrars (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Summary of Alumni Responses to 6/9/93 Letter, 1993-08-19 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Interdisciplinary Programs (Box 2, Folder 27)
- American, Latin American Studies, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Comparative Literature/Modern Thought (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Languages/Linguistics, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Music/Art, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- East Asian Studies (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Anthropology, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Food Research Institute, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Political Science/International Relations (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Psychology, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Political Science, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Biological Sciences, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Computer Science, Math, Computational Science, AStatistics, Operations Research, Symbolic Systems, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Earth Sciences (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Student Resources, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Center For Teaching and Learning (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Overseas Studies, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Continuing Studies/Summer Session, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Graduate School of Education (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Graduate School of Law, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Graduate School of Medicine, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Graduate School of Business, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Study of Undergraduate Education at Stanford: Student Advisory Group on Undergraduate Education Report to Commission, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Student Telephone Survey by ASSU, 1994-04-14 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Various Reports and Articles (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Transcripts, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Drexel Information, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Yale Programs of Study, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Commission Final Report [draft], 1994-07-25 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Appendix 3: Data (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Various Booklets and Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Newspaper Articles 2/1993- 6/1994, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Report Printing (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Dinner, 1994-10 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Outside Inquiries (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Background Reading (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Letters (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Research for The Commission (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Follow-up (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Geoff (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Current, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Commission Letters - Samples (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Chron File (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Charge (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Various Curriculums (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Commissioners (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence: Alphabetical (Box 3)
- James J. Sheehan Correspondence: Alphabetical (Box 3)
- Chron File 12/15-93 - 6/15/94, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Alumni Comments (Box 4)
- News Clippings 1/26/93 - 6/29/94, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Breadth Requirements Subcommittee (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Survey to Freshman and Sophomore's Faculty Advisors (Box 4)
- Advising Questionaires to Students (93-94) - Memo From Todd Benson with Survey 10/23/94, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Report of Subcommittee on Academic Environment Part 1: General Advising, 1994-05-02 (Box 4)